Guide to the William Ward Watkin family papers, 1899-1999 MS 508
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Ward Watkin family papers
1899-1999
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Watkin, William Ward, 1886-1952
MS 508
5.5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Correspondence, photographs, family trees, vital records and other genealogical material related to the Watkin family of Houston, TX (1910s-current) and of Danville, Pennsylvania (late 19th century). William Ward Watkin (1886-1952) was the first Supervising Architect of Rice Institute and the first chair of the Dept. of Architecture at Rice Institute. His daughter, Ray Watkin Strange, is a Rice graduate and significant supporter of Rice University and the Fondren Library.
Biographical Note
William Ward Watkin was born in Boston, Massachusetts, on January 21, 1886. His parents were Fred W. Watkin and Mary Hancock Watkin. Watkin grew up in Pennsylvania, the home state of his mother's family. He graduated from Danville High School in 1903 and entered the University of Pennsylvania, pursuing the study of architecture under Paul Phillipe Cret. Following his graduation in 1908, Watkin spent one year traveling in Europe, principally in England.
Upon his return from Europe, Watkin joined the Boston office of Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson, then one of the most prominent architectural firms in the United States. At the time of Watkin's employment, 1909, Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson had received the commission to produce a campus plan and to design the initial buildings of the Rice Institute in Houston, Texas.
Watkin worked on the development of both the campus plan and the building plan in the office; when construction was to begin, in the summer of 1910, Watkin was sent to Houston to serve as Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson's representative supervisor. In this capacity Watkin not only oversaw the construction of the initial Institute group--the Administration Building, the Mechanical laboratory and Powerhouse, and the North and South residence halls - but most of the Institute's subsequent development: the Physics laboratory (1913-1915), east Hall (1913-1914), West Hall (1915-1916), three proposed President's houses (1913, 1915, 1923-1924), the Field House (1920), the Chemistry Laboratory (1923-1925), a proposed Alumni Hall (1927), two proposed libraries (1927, 1940-1941), and the Founder's Statue (1927-1930). Watkin himself was to design the Faculty Club - Cohen House (1927), Rice Stadium (1938), and the Naval ROTC building (1941). He also served as consulting architect to Staub and Rather in the design and construction of the Fondren Library (1946-1949), M.D. Anderson Hall (1946-1947), and the Abercrombie Laboratory (1947-1948).
As supervising architect, Watkin worked closely with Dr. Edgar Odell Lovett, president of the Rice Institute. Lovett offered Watkin a faculty appointment and the Institute opened in the fall of 1912 with Watkin as instructor in architectural engineering. In the summer of 1916 he was made an assistant professor and in 1922 he became a full professor. In 1914 the architecture faculty expanded to two, and to three in 1915. Rice awarded the first professional degrees in architecture in 1917. Watkin's efforts to provide his students with a thorough course in architectural studies led him to organize a traveling fellowship in 1928. Watkin's academic duties were not restricted to the Architecture department. He was also Curator of Grounds, Chairman of the Faculty Committee on Buildings and Grounds, and Chairman of the Faculty Committee on Outdoor Sports, a position which resulted in his serving a term as president of the Southwest Conference in 1920. At the time of his sabbatical in the 1928-1929 academic year, Watkin resigned the athletic committee post. He remained, however, head of Buildings and Grounds, as his resignation of this post was not accepted by Dr. Lovett. During World War II, Watkin chaired the Committee on Air Raid protection and Civilian defense.
As early as 1912 Watkin was accepting independent architectural commissions. Between 1913 and 1915 he entered into partnership with George Endress of Austin, practicing under the name Endress and Watkin. This firm was dissolved at the end of 1919 and Watkin thereafter practiced under his own name. Also in 1919 Watkin ceased his affiliation with Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson, though he continued to operate, on a commission basis, as supervisor for their Texas projects. In addition to practicing architecture, Watkin consulted on projects, and in 1933 he was appointed to the Board of Architectural Consultants, an advisory group connected with the design of the Federal Triangle in Washington, D.C.
During the teens and twenties, Watkin wrote articles for journals, primarily dealing with Houston, its growth and development, and the implications these held for the city's architecture. Watkin contributed descriptive pieces on the Rice Institute to Progressive Houston and the Southern Architectural Review, Houston's short-lived architectural magazine. Not until the late twenties did he become more involved in research and writing. In 1930 the Rice Institute Pamphlet published a series of lectures Watkin had given on the new architecture in Europe; Pencil Points reprinted these in 1931. Watkin wrote two additional essays for Pencil Points, one published in 1931 on new directions in ecclesiastical architecture, and another in 1932. This former essay was something of a prolegomena to Watkin's first book, The Church of Tomorrow published in 1936. In 1951 Watkin's second book, Planning and Building the Modern Church, was published. At the time of his death he was planning to write a book on architecture in Texas.
Watkin had numerous academic and professional associations. He was a member of the Houston Philosophical Society, the Texas Philosophical Society and the Houston Country Club. Watkin was a charter member of the Rice Institute Faculty Club. He had become a member of the American Institute of Architects in 1913, and was elected to the College of Fellows in 1949. Watkin was a communicant of Trinity Church.
William Ward Watkin died on June 24, 1952 from complications following surgery for a broken kneecap. He was survived by his wife, Josephine Cockrell Watkin, whom he had married in 1933. Watkin had previously been married to Annie Ray Townsend Watkin, who died in 1929. Their three children were Annie Ray Watkin Biehl Hoagland, Rosemary Watkin Barrick, and William Ward Watkin, Jr.
Excerpted from Stephen Fox's 1976 unpublished Guide to the Papers of William Ward Watkin in the Woodson Research Center of the Rice University.
Ray Watkin Strange was born Annie Ray Watkin, May 11, 1915, in Houston, Texas. She is the daughter of William Ward Watkin (1886-1956) and Annie Ray Townsend (1892-1929).
For further information on Ray Watkin Strange and husband Harry Hoagland, see Christopher Hartman's Advance man: The life and times of Harry Hoagland, Boston: Newbury Street Press, 2005.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, photographs, family trees, vital records and other genealogical material related to the Watkin family of Houston, TX (1910s-current) and of Pennsylvania. William Ward Watkin (1886-1952) was the first Supervising Architect of Rice Institute and the first chair of the Dept. of Architecture at Rice Institute. His daughter, Ray Watkin Strange, is a Rice graduate and significant supporter of Rice University and the Fondren Library.
Access Restriction
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This material was donated by Ray Watkin Hoagland Strange, daughter of William Ward Watkin, 2002-2005.
Related Material
See also William Ward Watkin papers, 1903-1956. The finding aid is available online at: http://archives.library.rice.edu/repositories/2/resources/979. Selected material from these papers have been digitized and are available at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/12394.
See also Ray Watkin Strange Research Materials for William Ward Watkin and the Rice Institute, 1917-1985, finding aid available online at http://archives.library.rice.edu/repositories/2/resources/953.
See also William Ward Watkin and Ray Watkin Hoagland [Strange] information/vertical files at Woodson Research Center.
See also Edgar Odell Lovett Presidential Papers for additional correspondence and information on the building of Rice campus and Rice Academics. Finding aid online at http://archives.library.rice.edu/repositories/2/resources/991.
Index Terms
Subjects
Architecture; Architects -- Texas; Universities and colleges
Document Types
photographs; genealogies (histories); corrrespondence
Places
Texas -- History
Subjects (Persons)
Strange, Ray Watkin Hoagland, 1915-2011; Watkin, Annie Ray Townsend, 1892-1929; Watkin, William Ward, Jr., General, 1919-2001; Watkin, William Ward, 1886-1952
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University.
- Series I: Family genealogy and correspondence, 1920-1986, and undated, 245506
  - Watkin family tree, 245538 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Watkin genealogy in England; corresp. With genealogist, 245537 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History of Watkin family as builders in England, 245536 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Watkin in Northampton, England, 245535 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Guildhall, Northampton, 245534 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Northamptonshire, England record office re: George Lambley, Mary Watkin and descendants, 245533 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Watkin family genealogy in England and Flatbush, Brooklyn NY, 245532 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Watkins in Pennsylvania, 245531 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Watkin family Orange Grove, FL (property inherited from WWW's aunt and uncle, Dennis & Lucy Reay Bright), 245530 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Watkin family orange grove tax receipts, 245529 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Watkin family Bible records, 245528 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Watkin family vital records, 245527 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family marriage records, 245526 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mary Hancock Watkin papers, 245525 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sir Watkin Williams Wynn, 245524 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family newsclips, 245523 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Family deeds, 245522 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Family crests: Watkin, Hancock, 245521 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - William Hancock family genealogy, 245520 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Watkin family genealogy notes, 245519 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Watkin family indirect lines, 245518 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Watkin-Reay genealogy in England, 245517 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reay family notes & records, 245516 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reay family –genealogist correspondence, 245515 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Watkin family, 1920s-80s, 245514 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: W.W. Watkin, 245513 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: W.W. Watkin with family, 245512 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: W. W. Watkin & Josephine Watkin, 1930s-40s, 245511 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence & photos: M/M W.W. Watkin, 245510 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence & notes: Hancock-Watkin Chickering piano, 245509 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Evaluation of Biological Rate Parameters and Inhibitory Effects in Activated Sludge, Andrew Townsend Watkin, 1986, 245508 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Andrew T. Watkin reprints, 245507 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series II: Photographs, 245474
  General note
  See also Oversize Photographs in Box 9.
  - Watkin ancestors, 245505 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - John Watkin, 245504 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Frederick Wm. Watkin, 245503 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mary Hancock Watkin, 245502 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mary Hancock Watkin & William Ward Watkin, 245501 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - William Ward Watkin, 245500 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - William Ward Watkin at school, 245499 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bright house, Danville, PA, 245498 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annie Ray Watkin's bridge club at Mrs. Ethel Armstrong's new house on Bissonnet, winter 1928-29, 245497 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New Orleans, LA relatives, 245496 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - WWW children, 245495 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - WWW children (negatives), 245494 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Childhood friends, 245493 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - J.W. Northrup, 245492 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - W.W. Watkin family trip to Houlgate, France, 1925 postcards, 245491 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - W.W. Watkin trip abroad, 1928-29, 245490 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Travis Park Methodist Church, San Antonio, TX, 1996 [site of June 1, 1914 wedding of Annie Ray Townsend to William Ward Watkin], 245489 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - W.W. Watkin office groups, 245488 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - W.W. Watkin, Jr. family, 245487 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - W.W. Watkin, Jr. & family, 245486 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Carol & W.W. Watkin, Jr., 245485 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - W.W. Watkin, III graduation from Westpoint, 1975, 245484 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Rosemary Watkin, 245483 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Barrick family, 245482 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - W.W. Watkin house, Caroline St., Houston, TX, 245481 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Oakdale house for Rice professors, 245480 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Rice-related, 245479 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - M/M W.W. Watkin groups, 245478 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Bessy Kirby party at Houston Country Club, 1920s, 245477 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Negatives, 245476 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Photocopies of photographs, 245475 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Series III: William Ward Watkin, Jr., 245467
  - Correspondence and newsclips, 245473 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Biographical materials, 245472 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Family materials, 245471 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Army career materials, 245470 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Death, 3-1-01, 245469 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sympathy correspondence/cards, 245468 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series IV: William Ward Watkin, 1899-1999, 245438
  - Confirmation certificate, 1899, 245466 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Danville High School, PA, 245465 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - College English papers, 1904-05, 245464 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Architectural Society of Univ. of PA certificate, 245463 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Record: Class of 1909, University of Pennsylvania, 245462 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1916, 245461 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, misc., 1920s-, 245460 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Instructions to architecture office, 1928, 245459 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rice business card, 245458 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Expenses in Europe? 1928-29, 245457 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - House, 5009 Caroline, Houston, TX, 245456 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Houston Ship Channel property, 245455 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Rental property, 245454 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Legal, 245453 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 245452 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Newsclips, 245451 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Rice related, 245450 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Biographical materials, 245449 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles by and about WWW, 245448 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Memorial book, 6-24-1952, 245447 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, memorials, sympathy letters, 1952, 245446 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - WWW estate, 1952-, 245445 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Danville, PA scrapbooks, 245444 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Danville, PA photo album, 245443 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - History of Columbia and Montour Counties, Pennsylvania Illustrated, 1887, 245442 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Flying Owls; Rice Institute from the Air, 1921, 245441 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Guide to the Papers of William Ward Watkin in the Woodson Research Center of the Rice University Library," compiled by Stephen Fox, 1976, 245440 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Fondren Library and the Woodson Research Center present the William Ward Watkin On-line Exhibit," Nov. 2, 1999, 245439 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series V: Oversize materials, 245422
  - Annie Ray Watkin, Kinkaid School certificate, 1930, 245437 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Annie Ray Watkin, Chatham Hall Diploma, 1932, 245436 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Annie Ray Watkin, Bachelors of Arts, Rice Institute, 1936, 245435 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Ray Watkin Biehl, Masters of Arts, Rice Institute, 1944, 245434 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Subseries A: Photos, 245423
    - William Ward Watkin, 1886, Danville, PA, 245433 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Ella C. Myers wedding to Edward G. Pearson, 1936, 245432 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Rosemary Watkin (2), 245431 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Ray Watkin Biehl (3), 245430 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Annie Ray Watkin (3), 245429 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Florence Bell Townsend (sister of Annie Ray Townsend Watkin) in group, 245428 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - William Ward Watkin, 1943, 245427 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - William Ward Watkin, 1924, 245426 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - Annie Ray Townsend Watkin & Annie Ray Watkin, 245425 (Box 9, Folder -)
    - First class at Rice Institute, Oct. 1912, 245424 (Box 9, Folder -)
      General Note
      Items in folder: San Antonio Spring Fiesta, Court of the Battle of Flowers, Apr. 24, 1913; Duchess of Aurora, Annie Ray Townsend
  - Subseries B: Painting
    - framed oil painting of Annie Ray Townsend Watkin (Box 10)
- Series VI: Addendum
  - The Church of Tomorrow by William Ward Watkin; inscribed from WWW to daughter, Annie Ray, 1936 (Box 11)
  - Danville, Montour County, Pennsylvania, 1881 (Box 11)
    General
    inscribed "to Mama from Aunt Lucy, Nov. 14, 1884" inscribed "to Wm Watkin from his mother, Nov. 14, 1914"
  - William W. Watkin, Jr. family, schooling (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - William W. Watkin, Jr. career (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: William W. Watkin, Jr. in Vietnam, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - William W. Watkin, Jr. in Vietnam, 1965-1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: family, 1950-1970s (Box 11, Folder 5)